בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody.
Today's דף Daf is
מ, Mem, 40, and we're in the middle of a nice סוגיה
Sugya on, is this working? Hold on. Sorry,
give me one second. Yeah, I guess so. All right, and we're
in the middle of a nice סוגיה Sugya on, what do you
call it, on ביקור חולים. Bikur cholim. And now we continue here,
I'm just sorry. Yeah,
I don't know if this is working. Starting this again. All right,
fine. All right, so today's דף Daf is דף Daf מ Mem
and we're in the middle of the whole discussion about ביקור חולים
Bikur cholim because the whole question is somebody who's מודר הנאה, Mudar
hana'ah, can he go ahead and do ביקור חולים Bikur cholim for
somebody else? And we pick up about on ל"ט עמוד ב, Lamed
tet amud bet, one,
two, two just two lines actually down on the wide line. Okay,
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, ביקור חולים אין לה שיעור, Bikur cholim ein
lah shiur, there is no limit to ביקור חולים. Bikur cholim. מאי
אין לה שיעור? Mai ein lah shiur? What does it mean there's
no limit? סבר רב יוסף למימר, Savar Rav Yosef lemeimar, Rav Yosef
thought that it meant אין שיעור למתן שכרה, Ein shiur lematan secharah,
that the reward for doing ביקור חולים Bikur cholim is limitless. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye, so Abaye
said to him, וכל מצוה מי יש לה שיעור? Vechol mitzvah mi
yesh lah shiur? And how about all other מצות? Mitzvot? What, does
that mean to suggest that ביקור חולים Bikur cholim is unique?
Since when do other מצות Mitzvot have a limit to the amount
of reward that one gets for performing them? מי יש לה שיעור
למתן שכרן? Mi yesh lah shiur lematan secharan? והתנן, Vehatnan, we learned
in a משנה, Mishnah, הוי זהיר במצוה קלה כבחמורה, Hevei zahir bemitzvah
kalah kebachamurah, be as zealous or as scrupulous by a light מצוה
Mitzvah as by a heavy מצוה, Mitzvah, שאין אתה יודע מתן שכרן
של מצות, She'ein atah yodeia matan secharan shel mitzvot, you don't know
the amount of reward for the various מצות. Mitzvot. So, I mean
presumably the point being, maybe it's possible that some מצות Mitzvot are
more than others and some מצות Mitzvot are endless the amount of
reward, but to highlight that by ביקור חולים Bikur cholim would suggest
that that's not true by others and we don't know, maybe
all others fall into that category. Again, it's not exactly clear what
the objection is. Maybe it's true, maybe there are other מצות Mitzvot
that are in that category, but maybe specifically ביקור חולים Bikur cholim
is one of them. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara continues, אלא אמר
אביי, Ela amar Abaye, so rather Abaye says, אפילו גדול אצל קטן,
Afilu gadol etzel katan, אין לה שיעור, Ein lah shiur, meaning in
terms of quantifying and measuring things, even if somebody is an important
person, he should not say, well, you know what, this guy, he's
like a lower class guy. I'll let people from his strata of
society go visit him, it's not my honor to go ahead and
visit him. No, even a גדול אצל קטן, Gadol etzel katan, somebody
that's very, of a very high status should go and do a
ביקור חולים Bikur cholim call to anybody even somebody who is in
society seen of as a lower status. You know, you see this,
I don't know about ביקור חולים, Bikur cholim, you see this during
שבעה Shiva calls, you know, that people
was like, somebody who might be somebody nobody knows or whatever and
then some really important person comes and pays a visit because I
knew your mother back when or whatever, and people don't feel like,
oh, I can't pay a שבעה Shiva call, like I'm too חשוב
Chashuv for this person, you know. So that's actually a very positive
thing and the גמרא Gemara is saying it here too in terms
of ביקור חולים. Bikur cholim. So the גמרא Gemara says, where were
we? Okay, גדול
אצל קטן.
Gadol etzel
katan. רבא
אמר,
Rava
amar,
Rava has another interpretation, אפילו מאה פעמים ביום. Afilu me'ah pe'amim bayom.
Don't say, check, did my ביקור חולים Bikur cholim call for the
day, don't have to go back again. If somebody is sick and
nobody is visiting them and
they need human contact, I mean before we're going to get to
this other aspect of ביקור חולים Bikur cholim in terms of just
taking care of a person's need and so on, but the most,
first of all, the basic one is just the human contact. So
if a person needs it, you can't just give yourself a pat
on the back and feel you've been יוצא Yotzei your חיוב. Chiyuv.
I mean it doesn't mean you have to go a hundred times,
but if it's needed and nobody else is doing it, then
you're not done just because you did it once. Yeah, for many
sick people.
Oh, I guess it could mean that too,
that even if there are many sick people, you're not יוצא Yotzei
by going to one person. I was sort of thinking about the
way this is used in השב תשיבם אפילו מאה פעמים Hashev teshivem
afilu me'ah pe'amim or no, הקם
תקים עמו אפילו מאה פעמים, Hakeim takem imo afilu me'ah pe'amim, so
it's like multiple times even with the same type of doing the
same thing literally the same thing multiple times. אמר רב אחא בר
חנינא, Amar Rav Acha bar Chanina, כל מבקר חולה נוטל אחד מששים
בצערו Kol mevaker choleh notel echad meshishim betza'aro or some have מחליו,
Michol'yo, okay,
anybody who visits a sick person takes away one-sixtieth of the person's
illness or you create a partial healing for the person. One also
wonders, are you taking it away because you're taking it upon yourself?
But anyway, I think there's a little ambiguity about that, but anyway,
it does say you're taking away one-sixtieth of his anguish or of
his sickness.
It says here בצערו, Betza'aro, not מחליו Michol'yo which would be different.
In other words, he's not taking it away from him, you're just
getting the
צער Tza'ar yourself.
Hmm, interesting, but that's not yet the גמרא's Gemara going to. continue
to read it, so let's take a look. Okay, and you will
see that there is a גרסא girsa on the side which is
מחליו. mechalyo. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אמרי ליה, Amri lei,
so, so אמר להו Amar lehu אם כן im ken ליעלו leielu
שיתין shitin וליקומי. v'likumi.
So why didn't sixty people just visit him and then he'll get
better? So אמר להו, Amar lehu, so he said to them, כאיסורייתא
ke'isuryata דבי d'bei רבי, Rabbi, like the מעשה, maiseh,
like the tenths of the house of רבי. Rabbi. We'll see what
that means in a minute. ובן u'ven גילו, gilo, and anyway this
is only true like somebody who's of the בן גילו, ben gilo,
literally like of his age, but means somehow of his מזל, mazal,
you know, somehow from the same whatever I don't know astrology, but
somehow from the same מזל mazal that has some effect that you're
able to help by some type of a sympathetic healing or something,
you know, being sympathetic like being sort of in sync with this
person, you know, remove some of his pain.
Okay, is that 60 men around שלמה? Shlomo?
ששים גיבורים סביב לה.
shishim
gibborim saviv lah.
That's interesting, I hadn't thought about that. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says
דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי Rabbi אומר, omer,
so what's this מעשה maiseh דבי d'bei רבי? Rabbi? רבי Rabbi אומר
omer בת bas הניזונית hanizonis מנכסי minichsei אחין, achin, if a daughter
is supported (remain greater in effect of the כתובה) Kesuvah from the
brothers' property, נוטלת noteles עישור issur נכסים nechasim when she comes to
get married,
so there she is, the father died, she's being supported by the
estate, it's time for her to get married, she gets a tenth
of the estate. So אמרו amru לו lo לרבי, l'Rabbi, that's her
assumed to be dowry. So אמרו amru לו lo לרבי, l'Rabbi, they
said to רבי, Rabbi, לדבריך l'divarecha מי mi שיש sheyesh לו lo
עשר eser בנות banos ובן u'ven אין ein לו, lo, so somebody
has ten daughters and doesn't have a son—ובן, u'ven, excuse me, מי
mi שיש sheyesh לו lo עשר eser בנות banos ובן, u'ven,
somebody has ten daughters and a son, אין ein לו lo לבן
laben במקום bimkom בנות banos כלום? klum? Does that mean the son
doesn't inherit anything? Because you're having to give away to each daughter
one tenth of the estate when they get married and there'll be
no inheritance left. Is that really true? אמר amar להן, lahen, he
said back to them, ראשונה rishona נוטלת noteles עישור issur נכסים, nechasim,
the first one takes a tenth of what's present, והשנייה v'hashniya במה
bema ששיירה, sheshi'ira, and the second one takes a tenth of what
remains afterwards, והשלישית v'hashlishis במה bema ששיירה, sheshi'ira, and the third takes
a tenth of what remains after the first two. Okay, so therefore
it's not a tenth of the original estate, it's a tenth of
what is left. So I don't know, you can do the math,
what will that be if you have ten people, each one takes
a tenth? I'm sure there's some simple math equation to automatically figure
that out, I don't know what it is. Anyway, okay, so that's
all good if they get married one after the other. What if
they all get married on the same day? So then maybe they
all take a tenth of the current estate and maybe in that
case the son will lose out. And he says, no, even that's
not true. Even if it's all on the same day, וכגון שחלקום
בשווה, v'chegon shechalkum beshava, you figure out what would it have been
if they went sequentially, what would be the total amount that it
would have taken away from the estate if they had gone sequentially,
and then you divide it equally amongst all ten if they get
married on the same day. So you get, if they get married
on different days, the first one to get married actually gets a
bigger amount, but if all ten get married on the same day,
you figure out what that would have been if it were sequential
and you divide it equally. And that's the same of 60 people,
right? If I say well, 60 people one after another, it won't
get the guy better because each one will remove a 60th of
what's left. Or what if all 60 people go at the same
time? That should work? No, no, no, it would work the same
way. We'll figure it out what it would be sequential and we'll
divide it or whatever. All right, so
anyway, רב חלבו—and Rav Chelbo even that only works when it's a
בן ben גילו. gilo. So רב חלבו, Rav Chelbo, what?
It does get pretty
repetitive, yeah, it does, slowly, right. Now רב חלבו Rav Chelbo חלש,
chalash, רב חלבו Rav Chelbo got ill. נפיק nafik אכריז achriz רב
כהנא, Rav Kahana, רב כהנא Rav Kahana went out and made an
announcement. You see, the idea of making announcements was a—was
a—long-standing behavior. He went out and, you know, like a shul announcement.
Okay, put it in the ביקור חולים bikur cholim box in the
shul announcement. רב חלבו Rav Chelbo ביש, bish, and the announcement was
רב חלבו Rav Chelbo is sick. ולא איכא דקאתי, v'lo ika d'ka'asi,
but nobody came to visit him. The announcement didn't do any good.
אמר להו, Amar lehu, he went and he said to the people,
לא כך היה מעשה lo kach haya maiseh בתלמיד אחד מתלמידי רבי
עקיבא, betalmid echad mitalmidei Rabbi Akiva, one minute, don't you guys know
this story of a—of one of the students of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva שחלה, shechala, he got sick, ולא נכנסו חכמים לבקרו, v'lo nichnesu
chachamim levakaro, nobody came and visited him. ונכנס venichnas רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva לבקרו, levakaro, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva himself came to visit him.
That's again the גדולי הדור gedolei hador קטן. katan. ובשביל שכיבדו וריבצו
לפניו, Ubishvil shekibdo verivtzo lefanav, and because he, you know, he honored
him and he—and swept up in front of him,
so חיה, chaya, so he was brought back to life. How does
he translate כיבדו kibdo by the way? Does it mean honor him
or does it mean to like clean the house? Like לכבד את
הבית lechabed es habayis in high Hebrew is to clean the house,
right? What does it say there? In your English?
They swept the floor.
What—well there's two verbs here. What does it say other than swept?
Swept the floor and settled the dust.
כיבדו וריבצו. kibdo verivtzo. Settled the dust, right. So they explain כיבדו
kibdo as רבץ, rabatz, that's what I assumed, not honor. Okay, so
because they like swept and cleaned up, חיה chaya he was resuscitated,
he was brought back to life, took care of some very basic
needs. So אמר ליה amar lei רבי Rabbi החייתני, hechiyasani, he said
to him, רבי Rabbi you have given—you have brought me back to
life. יצא yatza רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva ודרש, vedarash, and as a
result רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva went out and—and expounded and taught, כל
מי שאינו מבקר. kol mi she'eino mevaker. anybody who does not visit
the sick is like they are spilling blood, because the visiting of
the sick, you know, gives them life. Now, it's attending to the
needs, but it's not just attending to the needs, it's attending to
the needs also right through human contact and what that means that
somebody who's there taking care of you is also obviously at the
sort of emotional, psychological level also very important. So anyway, if you
don't do it, you are, you know, you're not helping in this
person's recovery, so it's as though you are culpable for if for
this person's illness and if the person dies. So כי אתא רב
דימי אמר, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi
came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he said: by the way, so
that was the end of what of, you know, of רב כהנא.
Rav Kahana. He gave and he gave everybody מוסר, mussar, but you
notice what it doesn't say? It doesn't say that then they all
went to pray. They all listened and then they went to do
a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call to רב חלבו. Rav Helbo. This
was the מוסר, mussar, okay? Whether it, whether it actually was successful
in motivating people is a different question. Now, כי אתא רב דימי,
Ki ata Rav Dimi, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ
ישראל אמר, Eretz Yisrael amar, he said: כל המבקר חולה גורם לו
שיחיה, kol hamevaker chole gorem lo sheyichye, anybody who visits the sick
person helps him, brings him back to life; וכל מי שאינו
מבקר את החולה יש גורם לו שימות, vechol mi she'eino mevaker es
hachole yesh gorem lo sheyamus,
actually causes him to die. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי גרמא,
mai grama, what do you mean causes? אילימא כל המבקר חולה מבקש
עליו רחמים שיחיה, ileima kol hamevaker chole mevakesh alav rachamim sheyichye, it's
in that
anybody who visits the sick person will pray for him that he
will be brought to life; וכל
שאינו מבקר את החולה מבקש עליו רחמים שימות, vechol she'eino mevaker es
hachole mevakesh alav rachamim sheyamus,
will pray pray for him that he'll die? שימות סלקא דעתך? sheyamus
salka deitach? That that could be true? That somebody who doesn't visit
him prays for him to die? Who would pray for him to
die? אלא כל שאינו מבקר חולה אין מבקש עליו רחמים לא שיחיה
ולא שימות. ela kol she'eino mevaker chole ein mevakesh alav rachamim lo
sheyichye velo sheyamus. No,
the problem is just the passivity. That anybody who doesn't visit isn't
praying for him to get better or to get worse, but even
though he's not praying for him to get worse, he's also not
praying for him to get better, which means he's basically not concerned
with his person's welfare and therefore, even though he's not actively doing
anything to hurt him, the passive lack of helping him to get
any better makes him culpable if this person actually gets worse. Now,
of course, what's interesting is the shift of gears, right? The statement,
I mean, the Rabbi Akiva statement would have us thinking in very
practical terms, right, about taking care of the needs. Even the earlier
statement about נוטלו אחד מחליו, notlo echad mecholyov, okay, it's still not
about prayer, it's about something maybe I don't know, a little metaphysical,
right, but it's still not about prayer, and then the whole shift
that it's about, you know, whether you pray or you don't pray
for the person. It's quite fascinating how, I mean, I don't know
the answer why the סתמא דגמרא stama deGemara completely sort of shifted
it to be about prayer. But it still winds up making the
same statement. You're there, you're taking care of the person one way
or another by praying, taking care of the needs, the emotional connection,
you're helping them get better; you're not there, you're not actively hurting
them, but you're passively not helping them and therefore you're culpable. It's
sort of like the גמרא Gemara that says anyone anybody who is
אינו עוסק בפריה ורביה eino osek bepirya verivya כאילו שופך דמים, ke'ilu
shofech damim, right, is as if they spilled blood because they're not
bringing new life into the world. So the passive non-helping, you know,
if you're not helping you're hurting, you know, then it's actually like
seen like you're contributing to the person getting worse. Now there's a
fascinating ר"ן Ran here. That's פשט דגמרא, pshat deGemara, and then okay,
there's another nice גמרא Gemara about ביקור חולים. bikur cholim. But there's
a fascinating ר"ן Ran here that's very, very important in discussions of
medical ethics, which you would not have expected at all from this
גמרא Gemara related to this גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at
the ר"ן Ran on the top of of the page. אין מבקש
עליו רחמים לא שיחיה ולא שימות. ein mevakesh alav rachamim lo sheyichye
velo sheyamus. He says: נראה בעיני דהכי קאמר, nireh be'einai dehachi ka'amar,
it seems to me that this is what the גמרא Gemara is
getting at. פעמים שצריך לבקש רחמים על החולה שימות, pe'amim shetzarich levakesh
rachamim al hachole sheyamus, that actually there are times where you should
pray be praying for someone to
die, כגון דמצטער חולה דחייביה הרבה, kegon demitzta'er chole dechayov harbe, like
somebody is in a lot of pain and suffering, ואי אפשר לו
שיחיה, ve'i efshar lo sheyichye, and they are terminal. Okay, there's no
hope for recovery, they're in a lot of pain and suffering, the
best you could want for this person is that they should pass
easily, right, that it should not be a prolonged period of dying
and suffering. כי דאמרינן בפרק הנושא, ki de'amrinan bePerek Hanose, as we
say in the chapter of Hanose, דכיון דחזיא אמתיה דרבי דעל כמה
זימנין לבית הכסא, dekeivan dechazya amtei deRebbi de'al kama zimnin leveis hakisei,
Rabbi's maidservant saw that a number, multiple times, you know, in a
short period of time he had to go to the bathroom,
ואנח תפילין, ve'anach tefillin, and he'd then have to put his tefillin
back on, ומצטער, umitzta'er,
and he was in suffering. אמרה, amra, she said: יהי רצון שיכופו
עליונים את התחתונים, Yehi ratzon sheyachofu elyonim es hatachtonim, may it be
the will that the upper spheres are, you know, are victorious over
the lower, because all the תלמידים talmidim were praying that רבי Rebbi
would live, those were the lower spheres, and it's clear that up
in heaven it was his time to die. So she actually prayed
that he should just be able to die naturally and that his
death shouldn't be prolonged by the prayers of the students. כלומר דלימות
רבי, klomar delei-mus Rebbi,
so effectively she was praying that he should die. ומשום הכי קאמר
דמבקר חולה מועילו בתפלתו אפילו להחיות, umishum hachi ka'amar demevaker chole mo'ilo
bitfilaso afilu lehachyos, and because of this he says that somebody who
comes and visits it's helping the person to to even give the
person help the person come back to life, מפני שהיא תפילה יותר
מועלת, mipnei shehi tefilla yoser mo'eles,
because the prayer not just the person knows what is needed, but
the prayers with, you know, in the presence of... person will be
more effective. ומי שאינו מבקרו, u-mi she-eino mevakro,
and if you don't visit him, אין צריך לומר שאינו מועיל להחיותו,
ein tzarich lomar she-eino mo'il le-hachyoto, not only will your prayers not
help the person be brought to life, get better, if that's a
possibility, אלא אפילו היכא דאיכא להנאה במיתותא, ela afilu heicha de-ika lahna
be-mituta, even if all that was, even if the prayer was not
that he should get better, even if the prayer was a more
humble prayer, that it should be a simple passing, that he should
be able to just
die soon and without pain, without suffering, אפילו הא נמי לא מהניא,
afilu ha nami lo mahanya, even that little bit your prayers won't
work. So it's a very fascinating רן, Ran, right? He says, when
we talk about praying to die, like what's the גמרא Gemara talking
about praying to die? So he says, yeah, there are times you
want to be praying for somebody to die, that it's someone's time
and the person is suffering and you just want to pray that
they should have a, it shouldn't be prolonged and that should happen
quickly and naturally. And he's saying, sometimes even those prayers aren't heard,
right? Like if somebody's really terminal or whatever, like a prayer for
recovery is like, what are you praying for? If recovery isn't a
possibility, but you sometimes pray for a gentle and
a passing and sometimes unfortunately even that isn't heard and the person
it's prolonged. So that I think very
beautiful. Informal liturgy for that? I don't know, but maybe you could
just use רבי's Rebbi maid's invocation, יהי רצון שיכופו עליונים את התחתונים
yehi ratzon she-yechufu elyonim et ha-tachtonim or something.
They're putting together the
visit, right, with the prayer part.
Right, well that's what the גמרא Gemara does. He's working with the
גמרא. Gemara.
But now he's linking them together.
Right. But this, yes, right, but this is very important because in
all these discussions of course about
what's it called,
DNR and all, do you do heroic measures and how much do
you try to use medical interventions to slow down a natural death?
And a lot of the early material, I mean there's very little
in the גמרא Gemara about these end-of-life issues, we develop the whole
big halakhic system based on very few little hints in the גמרא,
Gemara, but anyway, but a very important distinction is between you want
to prolong, you don't want, you want to prolong life, you don't
want to prolong death, so therefore, and you don't want to interrupt
a natural process of
dying, but the balancing, the issue about prolonging life as opposed to
interrupting and stretching out a natural process of dying, and where, how
do you draw those lines? But that's an important guiding sort of
principle around deciding when to do various interventions. So the רן Ran
says it very beautifully, sometimes it's the time to die and the
most we can help for is to not stand in the way
and hope that that goes as
quickly and as painlessly as possible.
Does the רן Ran discuss personal autonomy?
No, no, no, the personal, that's another fascinating discussion about medical ethics
which is, רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein found like a backdoor
way to bring in personal autonomy because you know most of the
discussion is like, it's not our body, it's God's body, we don't
get to decide. So like maybe there's a discussion about personal autonomy
in cases where there is a גמרא Gemara that sort of sounds
like it, that if a person is חיי שעה, chayei sha'ah, if
a person is terminal, do they have to do certain types of
procedures that well it's a similar question, but they might not have
a חיוב, chiyuv, the וחי בהם ve-chai ba-hem or whatever which obligates
you to save life and preserve life and so on, does that
obligate you to do certain types of medical procedures that might extend
life for a brief period of time, but will involve a lot
of risk and involve suffering and so on? So there, there actually
is a גמרא בעבודה זרה Gemara be-Avodah Zarah that's used about that,
that actually seems to indicate you would have a certain degree of
autonomy.
But other types of areas it's less clear, but רב משה Rav
Moshe finds a sort of backdoor way to bring it in by
sort of saying like when person's wishes are not met, then that
can create an enormous amount
of angst, exactly, and not only suffering but angst or whatever that's
even more complicate the person's medical condition. So he's always inclined to
weigh in favor of the person's will by the presumption that doing
something against the will would be even more counterproductive. So that's how
רב משה Rav Moshe works it in. But the problem you have
is, well what if the person's like completely unconscious and in a
coma? You can't make that argument anymore. So yeah, all very interesting
questions.
Do you want to bring the idea of גוסס goses into that?
That there's a tradition
against interfering with
somebody when they were גוסס? goses? Yeah, I mean, but גוסס goses
is much, is not just terminal, גוסס goses is like very much
in the active process of dying, so alright. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay. רבא יומא קדמא דחלש, Rava yoma kadma de-chalash, רבא Rava on
the first day he got sick,
אמר להון, amar lehon, he said to them, to people that knew
him, his friends, לא תיגלו לאינשי, lo tiglu le-inshei,
don't tell people that I'm sick, דלא ליתרע מזלי, de-lo litra mazali,
that my, like it shouldn't be an עין הרע, ayin hara, my
מזל mazal should not get should not be just you know. made
bad. So people find out and maybe it reinforces the fact that
I'm sick, you know, and as long as it's not a public
matter, so maybe it'll pass quickly or whatever. But somehow the fact
that people find out about it makes it more of a reality.
Seems to be the idea. מכאן ואילך mikhan v'eilakh but once he
was sick for more than a day, so he saw it wasn't
passing quickly, אמר להון amar lehon he said to people, just like
people don't want to tell people they're pregnant yet or whatever other
types of things, right? I mean there's other practical reasons also, but
okay anyway. So anyway, first day he didn't want to tell. Once
it was clear that it was there to stay, he said, אמר
להון פוקו ואכריזו בשוקא, amar lehon puku v'akhrizu b'shuka, go and announce
it in a marketplace. Why? Why should we now announce it? דכל
דסני לי de'chol de'sani li because people that hate me, ריחדו לי,
richdu li, they'll be happy that I'm sick. Okay, why is that
a good thing? דכתיב de'chtiv and it says, בנפול אויבך אל תשמח,
binfol oyvecha al tismach, don't rejoice when your enemies when your enemies
stumble, when they fall down. Now what does that have to do,
what he's just so he's saying like, you know, the whatever they'll
they'll do a sin because they'll be happy about me? So the
real key is the end of the פסוק, pasuk, it says וגומר
v'gomer and if you look at the side, it quotes the in
the right-hand margin do you have this in your right-hand margin the
end of the פסוק? pasuk? No, it's in my גמרא, Gemara, no,
it says ובכשלו אל יגל לבך u'vikhshalo al yagel libecha and in
his stumbling do not let your heart rejoice, פן יראה ה' ורע
בעיניו pen yireh Hashem v'ra b'einav lest God see your rejoicing about
your enemy's downfall and the end of the פסוק pasuk is והשיב
מעליו אפו v'heshiv me'alav apo and therefore God will remove His anger
from your enemy because God will be more angry at you that
you're happy about what happens to your enemy. So therefore רבא Rava
says, let them be happy that I'm sick! If they're happy that
I'm sick, that'll mean that God will focus on them and take
away His anger from me and I'll get better. Okay, so a,
people that are happy, that'll be good for me, ודרחים לי u'derachim
li and people that love me, ליבעי רחמי, libai rachamei, then they'll
pray for me, so either way I'm going to win out. Believe
it, pray for me or they'll be happy that I'm sick and
then that'll also help. Okay, by the way, it's fascinating right because
רבא, Rava, who would expect somebody to open up a statement by
saying and people that hate me, this is what's going to happen.
So the reality is, you know, and what's his name at YU
has done a lot of work on on
רבא, Rava, Dr. Elman, you know, רבא Rava had a lot of
people that hated him in מחוזא Mahuza because he was a cosmopolitan
city and he basically was a very
strong Rabbi who told people when they were doing sins, and they
didn't like it. He had a lot of headache from this from
his community. So therefore he's saying that he knows that they're going
to be people that are going to be very happy that he's
sick. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Right, a little
bit of a diversion
back towards how Hashem will even back?
Well, exactly. Exactly.
Or in order to get back at this person for being happy,
God will make, you know, the other guy better. Anyway, but it
just also shows you that nothing has changed. Okay, even Rabbis like
רבא Rava had a lot of politics and headache. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רב, amar Rav, כל המבקר
את החולה ניצול מדינה של גיהנום, kol hamivakeir et hacholeh nitzol midina
shel Gehennam, anybody who visits the sick person is saved from the
punishment of גיהנום, Gehennam, שנאמר she'ne'emar as it says, אשרי משכיל אל
דל, ashrei maskil el dal, praised is the one that puts his
attention into the דל. dal. Now the דל dal normally means the
poor, but it could also mean the poor in health, you know,
to the sick. ביום רעה ימלטהו ה', b'yom ra'ah yimalteihu Hashem, and
the day of evil God will save him. אין דל אלא חולה,
ein dal ela choleh, and the דל dal the downtrodden the poor
is the sick person, שנאמר she'ne'emar מדלה יבצעני, midala yivtza'eni, from the
you know
from being ground down God will save me. אי נמי, i nami,
or it says from the following פסוק, pasuk, מדוע אתה ככה דל
בן המלך בבוקר בבוקר,
madua ata kach dal ben hamelech baboker
baboker, why are you so downtrodden or whatever poor the son of
the king every single morning? Somehow by we're supposed to understand that
that makes it clear that they were sick, I don't know.
אין רעה אלא גיהנום, ein ra'ah ela Gehennam, and evil is means
גיהנום, Gehennam, שנאמר she'ne'emar
כל פעל ה' למענהו, kol pa'al Hashem lama'aneihu, all God does is
for God's sake, וגם רשע ליום רעה, v'gam rasha l'yom ra'ah, even
the wicked person who is who is like designated for the day
of evil. So God created גיהנום Gehennam for the wicked, that's what
it means כל פעל ה', kol pa'al Hashem, God created it. ואי
בקר, v'i bikar, and if you do visit the sick person, מה
שכרו, mah secharo, what will be your reward? So the גמרא Gemara
says, מה שכרו, mah secharo, what will be your reward? כדאמרן, k'da'amran,
you just told us, ניצול מדינה של גיהנום, nitzol midina shel Gehennam,
you'll be saved from גיהנום, Gehennam, isn't that enough? אלא מה שכרו
בעולם הזה, ela mah secharo ba'olam hazeh, no, it's not enough. What
are you going to get rewarded in this world? So the following
פסוק, pasuk, ה' ישמרהו ויחייהו, Hashem yishmereihu v'ichayeihu,
God will preserve you and and give you life, ואושר בארץ, v'ushar
ba'aretz,
and well for goodness in the land, ואל תתנהו בנפש אויביו, ve'al
titneihu b'nefesh oyvav,
and will not give you over to the soul of your enemies.
So ה' ישמרהו, Hashem yishmereihu,
God will protect you, מיצר הרע, mi'yeitzer hara, from the evil inclination.
ויחייהו, v'ichayeihu, and give you life, מן הייסורין, min ha'yissurin, from this
anguish. The גמרא Gemara starts to point out that each one of
these is corresponds to how you help the sick person. So, you
know, sort of the the יצר הרע, yeitzer hara, I forget what
he says about the יצר הרע, yeitzer hara, but anyway, maybe the
יצר הרע yeitzer hara not to go visit the sick person, and
you chose to do the right thing, and God will ויחייהו, v'ichayeihu,
right, מן הייסורין, min ha'yissurin, because, you know, you were helping a
sick person that was suffering. ואושר בארץ, ve'ushar ba'aretz,
and happiness in the land, שיהיו הכל מתכבדים בו, sheyihiyu hakol miskabdim
bo,
everybody should give you honor and respect. And so the מהרש"א Maharsha
points out that that goes back to the idea that אפילו גדול
אצל קטן, afillu gadol eitzel katan, right, that people come even, you
know,
even people of a higher stature social standing will come and visit
the sick person. ואל תתנהו בנפש אויביו, ve'al tisneihu benefesh oyvav, and
not give you over to the soul of your enemies. So why
doesn't it just say your enemies? So to tell you שיהיו לו
רעים כנעמן, sheyihiyu lo rei'im keNa'aman, you'll get friends like נעמן Na'aman
had friends שריפאו את צרתו sheripu es tzaraso that they helped him
cure himself from his from his צרתו, tzaraso, right, and again notice
you have friends who help you with your problems, which is what
ביקור חולים bikur cholim is all about. You're a friend and you're
helping the person, you know, you're there for the person when he
has problems and specifically when he's got illness. ואל יזדמנו לו רעים
כרחבעם, ve'al yizdamnu lo rei'im keRechavam, and not friends like רחבעם. Rechavam.
This is by the way why the מהרש"א Maharsha says it says
נפש nefesh because it's about not just like it's about like, you
know, the connection that you have to your friends, you know, and
their advice, and
so you won't have friends friends like רחבעם Rechavam שחלקו את המלכות
shechilku es hamalchus that they didn't do good, that they actually led
to their advice caused the whole the kingdom to be divided. תניא,
tanya, so now we're going to talk about רחבעם Rechavam a little
bit, about what it means to have friends and with friends like
this who needs enemies type of a thing. That's like the נפש
אויביו, nefesh oyvav, friends who really are enemies. Okay, תניא, tanya, we
done a ברייתא, braisa, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar omer, אם יאמרו לך ילדים בנה, im yomeru lecha yeladim bneh,
if children tell you to build, וזקנים סתור, uzkeinim ssor, and elders
tell you to destroy
something, שמע לזקנים ואל תשמע לילדים. shma lizkeinim ve'al tishma liyeladim. שבנין
ילדים סתירה, shebinyan yeladim stirah,
the building of minors ultimately will be for is a destruction, וסתירת
זקנים בנין ustiras zkeinim binyan and the destruction of elders בנין binyan
is ultimately a building. Meaning so even if their advice looks, you
know, some advice on the surface looks positive and other advice on
the surface looks negative, trust in the wisdom of elders. Because things
that might look attractive if it's coming from those that lack the
wisdom ultimately can come to hurt you and to come to be
even more, you know, counterproductive and the same in the reverse. Okay,
וסימנא לדבר רחבעם בן שלמה, vesimana ladavar Rechavam ben Shlomo, and the
siman is רחבעם Rechavam
because he listened to the young people who said, you know, increase
the tax on the people and ultimately it led to the destruction,
to the tearing apart of the kingdom and maybe one could even
say eventually the destruction of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but minimally
to the tearing apart of the kingdom. And what the elders were
saying were saying go easy on the people, here, you know, maybe
that's seen as like a סתירה, stirah, like you are loosening your
your your reins of power, you're loosening your income, you're going easy,
you're not taxing them and so on. Ultimately that would have helped,
you know, the government, the kingdom much more. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי, Amar
Rav Sheshes brei deRav Idi, לא יסעוד אינש קצירה. lo yisod inash
ktzira. A person should not visit, there's some interesting Aramaic words here,
ליסעוד lisod like like which is like פוקד, pokeid, a person should
not visit a קצירה. ktzira. קצירה ktzira is an Aramaic word for
חולה, choleh, okay. I don't know exactly why, but it comes from
maybe what's קצר katzar to cut, I'm not sure where it comes
from, but anyway a person should not visit a a sick person
לא בתלת שעי קדמייתא, lo bislas sha'ei kadmayasa, not in the first
three hours of the day, ולא בתלת שעי בתרייתא velo bislas sha'ei
basrayasa and not in the last three hours of day דיומא deyoma
of the day. כי היכי דלא ליסח דעתיה מן רחמי, ki heichi
delo lisach da'ateih min rachamei, so that he should not so that
it should not, you know, sort of make him
despair of praying for the person. Why would it make him despair
of praying for the person? תלת שעי קדמייתא tlas sha'ei kadmayasa because
the first three hours רווחא דעתיה, ravcha da'ateih, the person actually, you
know, people often feel feel like better in the morning, they have
a burst of energy, so you'll say oh he's not doing so
bad, he looked pretty up and about, he looked pretty healthy to
me, so you won't pray for him as much. בתרייתא, basrayasa, the
last three hours, תקיף חולשיה takif chulsheih is when he's at his
worst, so you'll say what's going to do good to pray for
him, he's clearly he's clearly at death's door. So you so therefore
get him when he's in the middle so you'll feel properly motivated
to pray for him. Again it's interesting that it focuses on, you
know, the prayer as a core part of what the ביקור חולים
bikur cholim is all about. Because one could say if the ביקור
חולים bikur cholim is really about being there for the person and
supporting them and so on, then the last three hours of the
day דווקא, davka, you know, is maybe when he most needs you,
right, and he most needs that type of support that you can
offer. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבין אמר
רב, Amar Ravin amar Rav, מניין שהקדוש ברוך הוא זן את החולה,
minayin sheHakadosh Baruch Hu zan es hacholeh, how do you know that
God God feeds the sick person, presumably reflecting the idea that when
people are sick often they don't are not very hungry and don't
need, you know, and don't don't want a lot of food. So
who's sustaining them during that time if they're not eating so much?
God is. שנאמר, shenemar, it says השם יסעדנו על ערש דוי, Hashem
yisadeinu al eres devai, God will support him on the, you know,
on the bed of of anguish,
so of suffering. So God is the one and from the word
סעודה, seuda, לסעוד lisod to be to support, but also from the
word סעודה. seuda. So God is the one. that is feeding and
that is sustaining the person. ואמר רבין אמר רב, Ve'amar Ravin amar
Rav, מנין שהשכינה שרויה למעלה ממיטתו של חולה? minayin she'hashchina shruya lemala
mi'mitaso shel choleh? How do we know that God's presence hovers above
the sick person? שנאמר, She'ne'emar, as the verse says, השם יסעדנו על
ערש דוי. Hashem yis'adenu al eres devay. So God supports him, so
somehow support here is maybe understood to mean like not just סעודה
se'uda of like the סעודה, se'uda, but to literally support, so somehow
it's not exactly clear but somehow that means that God is at
the head of the bed supporting maybe the head of the person.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it was taught similarly, הנכנס לבקר
את החולה, hanichnas levaker et hacholeh, so if somebody comes to visit
the sick person, לא ישב לא אגבי המיטה, lo yeshev lo agabei
hamita, so if somebody comes to visit the sick person don't sit
on a couch, which is what a מיטה mita was, you know
one of those Roman couches, ולא על גבי ספסל velo al gabei
safsal or on a stool, ולא על גבי כיסא velo al gabei
kisse or a chair, אלא מתעטף ויושב על גבי קרקע, ella mita'atef
ve'yoshev al gabei karka, but sit on the ground, מפני שהשכינה שרויה
למעלה ממיטתו של חולה, mipnei she'hashchina shruya lemala mi'mitaso shel choleh, because
the divine presence is above the head of the חולה, choleh, so
you should not be sitting equal to where the divine presence is,
you need to be at a lower level, שנאמר השם יסעדנו על
ערש דוי. she'ne'emar Hashem yis'adenu al eres devay.
Okay, so that was the end for now of this very nice
long passage. It's not the only place that the גמרא Gemara talks
about ביקור חולים, bikur cholim, very powerful passages in the beginning of
ברכות Berachot if you remember about ייסורין של אהבה, yissurin shel ahava,
where it talks about people visiting people, and there's a lot of
גמרות Gemaras about ביקור חולים. bikur cholim. Okay, so now we turn
though to a different point which has nothing to do with ביקור
חולים bikur cholim and nothing to do with נדרים, Nedarim, but is
because we had a statement in the name of ואמר רבין אמר
רב, Ve'amar Ravin amar Rav, who was it? Of ואמר רבין אמר
רב, Ve'amar Ravin amar Rav, we have another statement of his, and
this is paralleled in another גמרא. Gemara. ואמר רבין אמר רב, Ve'amar
Ravin amar Rav, says Ravin in the name of
Rav, מטרא במערבא, mitra be'ma'arava, if there's rain in ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, סהדא רבא פרת, sahada rabba Perat, the big testimony to the
fact that there was rain in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is the
Euphrates. When the Euphrates is going very high on its banks and
it's like rushing water, so it's clear that what was happening was
that there was heavy rain in Israel and that fed into the
Euphrates. Now, not exactly clear why it's דווקא davka ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, there's a lot of places that might feed rain into the
Euphrates. You know, the מפרשים mefarshim say it's to be the assumption
that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is higher than the other lands, so
it's going to run down or run off into the Euphrates. Anyway,
but that means when we see here in בבל Bavel that the
Euphrates is high, we know that it was very rainy in Israel.
Now, this actually becomes significant הלכתא. halachically. ופליגא דשמואל, U'pliga de'Shmuel,
this argues on Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, De'amar Shmuel, נהרא מכיפיה מתבריך, nahara
mikafih mitbarech, a river
is blessed from its bedrock, which means that apparently rivers' water, where
does—I should have looked this up ahead of time—but where do like
rivers and lakes come from if they're natural? They come from underground
streams, right? Or do all rivers come from the ocean? כל הנחלים
הולכים אל הים. kol hanechalim holchim el hayam.
Or do they come from the runoff from mountains?
Or from springs? And lakes come from also from both, right?
Lakes come from—well, we're not really talking about lakes, but
I was just talking about rivers, so much of rivers come from—so
it depends I guess on the particular river and the particular, whether
it's primarily coming from the underground or from the mountains or from
the
rain.
But my guess would be that rivers that are fed by springs
are not as
strong, they're not as powerful. Okay, so that's important to know. Okay,
so anyway, because we'll see why it's going to have a very
relevant מקוה mikvah question. So Shmuel says rivers ultimately get more of
their—מכיפיה מתבריך—are mikafih mitbarech blessed, get more of their water from the
underground springs, and even if it's a heavy rain, it doesn't say
it here but in another place it says it, every drop that
comes from above is met with two drops from below. So somehow
Shmuel understood that even when it rains, that helps draw up the
water from below, but its primary source is the underground springs. Now,
the reason all this is relevant, I mean we'll read it in
a minute but I'll just tell you now, is there's a principle
that a מקוה, mikvah, collected rainwater, is only מטהר באשבורן, mitaher be'ashboren,
is only מטהר with sort of
settled unmoving water, whereas rivers and other sort of
natural bodies of water
are מטהר—lakes, rivers, etc.—even if it's like naturally standing water, like a
lake, but anything that ultimately comes from the ground
is מטהר בזוחלין, is a good מקוה mikvah even if water is
moving. So the question is what is a river? Is a river
fundamentally a natural body of water that comes from the ground, from
a wellspring, or is it a body of collected rainwater? And if
the majority of the water in the river right now is collected
rainwater, which would include also runoff of melted snow, so from what
I'm hearing from all of you that actually is a very high
occurrence in terms of rivers, then you've got a big problem, because
rivers run and they're moving, but if their majority is rainwater or
melted snow, הלכתא halachically they're a מקוה, mikvah, they're not a מים
חיים, mayim chayim, they're not considered something that comes ultimately from a
live source from below. Okay, so that's going to be very relevant.
So Shmuel's statement that every drop of rain from above is met
with two drops from below will say that a river never has
the status of a מקוה, mikvah, always has the status of מים
חיים. mayim chayim. And therefore you can always use it in, you
can always use it if it's running. But if you say that
no, that's not true, and that often a lot of the water
comes from the rain or the snow, then you're gonna have to
judge where this river's waters are from if you want to be
able to use it as a מקוה, mikvah, right? Because it's running
water.
Isn't it all a cycle anyway? Even water that comes from underground
sources is ultimately, I think, through absorption through the ground. Really?
It's not,
I mean, it originated underground.
Where did the water come
from? Because
from when God created the world. I mean, no, I'm saying the
world was created with water in the oceans and water underneath the
ground. Right, so ultimately, so that is true. So you're saying that
they get replenished ultimately from rainwater that's seeped back in? Yeah, I
think somehow once it gets absorbed into the ground and gets back
in, it gets like a, it's sort of like a תינוק שנשבה,
tinok shenishba, not, whatever, a קטן שנולד katan shenolad dummy type of
point at a certain stage, that's true. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says דאמר שמואל, da'amar Shmuel, okay, so פליגי דשמואל אדשמואל, pleigi
d'Shmuel a'd'Shmuel, this statement of שמואל Shmuel that the majority comes from
below argues on another statement of שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, da'amar Shmuel,
because שמואל Shmuel says אין המים מטהרים בזוחלין, ein hamayim metaharim b'zochalin,
water, you cannot use water if it's running, if it's
moving, אלא, ela, ha, you see, you thought we might not finish
with today's דף. daf. אלא פרת מיומי תשרי בלבד, ela Perat miyomei
Tishrei bilvad,
the only type of river you can use
which has moving water is the Euphrates during תשרי, Tishrei, during the
fall. Why? Because the argument would be that at any other time
other than תשרי, Tishrei, we would be afraid of either melted snow
or rainwater. I mean, you know, I guess in the spring you
have the melted snow issue, and the fall and winter you've got
the rain issue. So the only time where you don't have to
be afraid about rain and melted snow, whatever, is תשרי. Tishrei. But
any other time, he says, we've got to, it might be considered
majority rainwater, and you can't use it as moving water. So this
argues on his earlier statement, right? Because his earlier statement said we
can always assume that more of the water comes from below. And
this statement is saying that that's not the case. So we now
have the second statement of שמואל Shmuel and the earlier statement of
רבין אמר רב Ravin amar Rav that basically say, you know, sometimes
a lot of the river, a lot of the water in rivers
is from rainwater, which would mean you can't use them as a
מקוה mikvah if that might be the case. And now we're actually
going to see a practical implication of this by שמואל'ס Shmuel's father.
אבוה דשמואל עביד להו מקואתא לבנתיה ביומי ניסן, avuha d'Shmuel avid lehu
mikvatah l'banatei b'yomei Nisan,
he made for his daughters מקואות mikvahs in the springtime because the
springtime is when the snow would melt and the majority of the
water in the rivers would be rainwater or snow water, and therefore
the rivers could not be used. So then they would have to
use a מקוה. mikvah. ומרציפי בימי תשרי, umartzipi b'yomei Tishrei, and only
during the תשרי, Tishrei, or maybe it means the whole fall season
where the rivers could be used because the majority was not from
rainwater, so there they were using the rivers, so he made for
them mats. Why did he make for them mats? Because who wants
to actually go in a river and get your feet on the
rocks and in the mud and so on. Number one, it's a
חציצה chatzitzah problem, and two, it just might be a slippage problem
or getting your feet cut by the rocks. Okay, so basically they
would use the rivers only in תשרי Tishrei when they did not
have to be concerned about rainwater or snow. And it was only
when they were, and in all other times they would have to
use מקואות. mikvahs. So obviously you can imagine this is a big
נפקא מינא, nafka mina, right? If somebody basically tells you, I'm going
somewhere and there's not going to be any מקוה, mikvah, what can
I do etc? To that growth is to say, well, are there
natural bodies of water? Okay, but then first of all, if there's
a lake, you better find out if it's not a man-made lake,
because there definitely are some big lakes that are man-made. And if
it's a, you know, if it's an ocean, but if it's an
ocean or a natural lake, you're pretty good. I mean, again, I
think it depends, some lakes actually depending on the time of year
and depending on the lake might actually have this issue of rainwater,
but
lakes also are stationary, they're not moving, right? Then question is, what
do you with like a little bit of the little wavy type
of stuff that happens? But you know, but anyway, but so I'm
not giving a פסק psak obviously, but as a general rule, lakes
and oceans you're fine, if the lake isn't man-made. But rivers are
a big issue because rivers are moving and very often it might
be the majority coming from rainwater or melted snow. Okay, so that's
the big רן, Ran, the discussion in the רן Ran is a
couple of things. First of all, the רן Ran also wants to
know about even if the river isn't, even if it's not like
it's a very high level of water, the רן Ran says you
might, even if the normal sort of water level, you might have
to be concerned that it's from snow or rain if it's the
type of river that often
dries up. Okay, maybe this is relating to the things you guys
were saying. Meaning, if a river often dries up, right, and then
so it might get to its normal levels, but even at like
a not strong level, even a normal level might be because of
the rain and of the melted snow. I guess it's what you're
saying, if a river were to dry up if it primarily is
not coming from the underground. So then even at a normal level
you would have to be concerned that it might be from the
rain or the snow. That's one point he made. The other big
discussion he makes is how do we פסקן? pasken? רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam tries to פסקן pasken like what seems to be a very
minority... voice here, שמואל Shmuel that says that even when it rains
heavily you can assume it's coming from the underground, but the רן
Ran and like almost all other ראשונים Rishonim will say no, that's
clearly not true, clearly we פסקן pasken that if there's any serious,
any concern that it might be coming from rainwater or melted snow,
and it's moving water, you have to be concerned about that. Okay,
so that's number one, how do we פסקן? pasken? And then he
has another, a second possibility of being מקיל, meikel, which is he
says maybe it depends, maybe you could be מקיל meikel the following
way, that if even when, like here's my river,
right? Here's my river, okay, you know, here's my river during, during
when it's not, when it's just normal, and it hasn't been raining,
and it's not melted snow and so on, okay, and now because
of the extra rainwater, right, now there's all this rainwater, right, somehow
that makes it go, I don't know, like that makes it go
even to places it wouldn't have gone before.
Does that happen? Like it gets pushed into
tributaries or somehow tributaries?
Anyway, so he says like this, he says there's a, there is
a position that says that the part that you can't use because
it's running water that's now a majority rainwater is this section, is
the section that wouldn't have been a מקוה mikvah were it not
for the rain, additional rainwater. But this section, which anyway would have
been כשר kosher without the additional rainwater, even though now it's a
majority rainwater, it doesn't פסול posul this section from being used. Okay,
so you get it? I mean it's true, now you have a
majority rainwater, but it's like, who needed you? Who needed the rainwater?
This would have been כשר kosher without the rainwater and it wouldn't
have, this would have been a מקוה mikvah without the rainwater that
could have been used while it was running. So that's another possibility
of maybe being lenient and he has a long discussion about that.
Okay, but that's some of what this long length of the רן
Ran is. But as I said, the גמרא Gemara itself is not
that conceptually difficult to understand. It's pretty important in terms of, as
far as הלכה halacha is concerned. Okay, let's read a little bit
more and we'll finish today's דף, daf, get off easy today, it's
a real bonus for your vacation, for your Fourth of July vacation.
Okay, אמר רבי אמי אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Ami Amar Rav, מאי
דכתיב, mai d'chiv, what's meant by the פסוק, pasuk, ואתה בן אדם
עשה לך כלי גולה? ve'ata ben adam asei lecha k'lei gola? Make
for yourself vessels of, of the exile. זו נר וקערה, zo ner
u'kearah, this is a candle and a plate. Like what do you
take when you're sort of going on camping? What do you take
when you're going into exile? So what are the minimum vessels that
you need? So a candle and a plate, ושטיח, u'shatiach, and a
mat, something to go to sleep on as you're going to be
traveling and you're not going to be having a bed. You know,
I don't know why you don't also need like a tent to
protect you from the elements. Anyway, בחוסר כל, b'choser kol, so now
in a similar sense we're sort of saying,
so anyway what is this doing here before we first mention that,
what does that have to do with anything? So, so some say
the real גירסא girsa is not אמר רב אמי אמר רב, Amar
Rav Ami Amar Rav, it's אמר רבין אמר רב. Amar Ravin Amar
Rav. So it's a series of statements of אמר רבין אמר רב,
Amar Ravin Amar Rav, right? The first אמר רבין אמר רב Amar
Ravin Amar Rav was from before, which was I think God is
on the head of, yes, God is on the head of the
sick person. And then it's אמר רבין אמר רב Amar Ravin Amar
Rav about the Euphrates from the rain that's in בבל. Bavel. And
now, I mean from the rain that's in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
And now it's אמר רבין אמר רב Amar Ravin Amar Rav just
interpreting this פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so these three at least at the
face of it have nothing to do with one another. Okay, so
now that we're talking about what are like some minimum things that
are necessary for survival, so here we look in the מקרא Mikra
where it says בחוסר כל, b'choser kol, that you will be lacking
everything. So what does it mean to not have anything? אמר רבי
אמי אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Ami Amar Rav, בלא נר, belo ner,
you won't even have a candle. בלא שלחן, belo shulchan, and not
a table. רב חסדא אמר, Rav Hisda amar, בלא אשה, belo isha,
without a wife. רב
ששת אמר, Rav Sheshet amar, בלא שמש, belo shamash, without an attendant.
So I keep on telling all of you that I'm in, nobody
has signed up yet to be my, like my שמש. shamash. So
that's an open, plus a lot of בחוסר כל. b'choser kol. Okay.
רב נחמן אמר, Rav Nachman amar, בלא דעה, belo de'ah, without intellect,
that if you don't have intellect you've, you've really got nothing. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, it's in the ברייתא, Baraita, בלא מלח, belo melach,
without salt, which is necessary to preserve or give a little taste
of things. ובלא רבב, u'belo revav, and without something to dip something
in, without some oil to dip your bread in. Okay. And אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says נקטינן, naktinan, we take the position
אין עני אלא בדעה, ein ani ela b'de'ah, to really, what being
poor means, it's sort of like איזהו עשיר השמח בחלקו, eizehu ashir
hasameach b'chelko, what really being poor is, it's about a, you know,
it's like, it's, one could say like a poor is about a
state of mind. Okay, I mean it doesn't mean poor means it's
about not being, being, not having intellect, or does he mean even
being poor, you know the whole state, the whole famous story, right,
about whatever, about this guy that was suffering so much and he
says to the רבי, Rebbe, you know, I don't, you know, how
am I supposed to, you know, get by? Like I have nothing,
my life is so miserable. Says, you know, go see this following,
צדיק tzaddik or whatever, and he goes to this person and he
sees, you know, whatever how miserable he is, covered in scabs and,
you know, has nothing. He says, I don't understand how are you
able to be happy with all these bad things that are happening,
have happened to you through your life? And he says, or says,
I don't understand, nothing bad has ever happened to me in my
life. So, I told that story very quickly and I didn't
the intelligence if you have intelligence you can figure out how to
manage how to get through life and manage everything else and if
you don't have intelligence then you're really going to have troubles. Okay,
אלא בדעה. ela bedeya. במערבי אמר, Bemaravi amar, דדא בי כולה בי.
da de-bi kula bi.
If you have intelligence you've got everything. דלא דא בי de-la da
bi if you don't have intelligence מה בי mah bi then what
then what do you have? Okay? דקני דא קני מה
חסר. de-kane da kane ma chasar. If you acquire this, intelligence, then
you won't be lacking anything. דלא קני de-la kane and if you
don't acquire this מה קני mah kane then what is good anything
that you would have acquired? Okay, so all similar to איזהו עשיר
השמח בחלקו eizehu ashir hasameach bechelko right? Within that type of a
genre of these statements. Okay, we will continue with this tomorrow on
the real July 4th and the real שבעה עשר בתמוז. Shiva Asar
B'Tammuz.